Hi. This is Matt Baker. Recently I did a pair
of videos on the words Israel and Palestine and
how each of these words can mean different
things, depending on the context. However,
two words that I didn't go into much detail on
(even though they obviously came up) were Zionism
and Anti-Zionism. So I figured a third video
was needed in order to clear a few things up.
First off, in the Israel video, I made it seem as
if Anti-Zionism was simply being critical of the
actions of the current Israeli government.
But this is actually not the case because,
as several people pointed out in the comments,
many Zionists also oppose the actions of the
current Israeli government. In other words I
didn't really get to the heart of the difference
between Zionists and Anti-Zionists. So
that’s what I’m going to do right now.
Let me start by sharing a very basic
definition of Zionism. At its core,
Zionism is simply: Support for the continued
existence of Israel as a Jewish state. So,
regardless of what you think about what is
happening in Gaza and regardless of whether
or not you think Palestinians deserve their own
state, if you think Israel should continue to
exist as it does right now (meaning as a
country with a uniquely Jewish identity),
then you are a Zionist. Now, within this broad
definition, Zionism can obviously take a multitude
of different forms. Let me describe at least
two, starting with the most extreme version.
There are some Zionists who are undeniably
racist and Islamophobic towards Palestinians,
who have participated in genocidal war
crimes against them, and who have supported
illegal settlements in Palestinian
areas. This brand of Zionist would
like to see Gaza and the West Bank cleared of
all Arabs so that Israel could look like this.
However, there are also other Zionists (often
called Liberal Zionists) who strongly oppose
the War on Gaza and who even acknowledge that
a genocide has occurred there. These Zionists
want Palestinians to have freedom, safety, and
peace but see some sort of a two-state solution
as the best way forward. Because a two-state
solution would involve the continued existence
of Israel as a Jewish state alongside a new,
fully independent Palestinian state, anyone who
favors a two-state solution (even if they are
a Palestinian) is, by definition, a Zionist.
Okay, let’s now take a look at Anti-Zionism,
starting with its most extreme form. There are
some Anti-Zionists who are undeniably antisemitic,
hating both the Jewish people as a whole as
well as the State of Israel. They tend to
use the same tropes against Israel that have been
used against Jews for centuries and would like to
see the Middle East completely cleared of all
Jews so that Palestine would look like this.
However, there are also other Anti-Zionists
(including Anti-Zionist Jews) who simply
see Zionism as a bad idea because it’s deeply
rooted in 19th century ideas about nationalism,
which are now outdated. This type of Anti-Zionism
acknowledges that the Zionist project (even if its
aims were good) necessitated the expulsion of
Palestinians and continues to necessitate their
occupation and denial of rights (which is not
good). But here's the part that I really want
to highlight. These Anti-Zionists don't want
to make things right by kicking out all of the
Israeli Jews. No, they want the Israeli Jews to
continue to live safely where they do right now,
with all their rights and freedoms. The only
difference is that they want the Palestinians
to also share in those same rights and freedoms.
And in order for that to make happen, they see a
one-state solution as the best way forward—a
state that would be equally Jewish and Arab.
So, because this sort of one-state solution would
involve a state that wouldn’t be explicitly just
Jewish, anyone who favors a one-state solution
like this is, by definition, an Anti-Zionist.
So, I still stand by my earlier statement that
Anti-Zionism doesn't have to be antisemitic,
just like Zionism doesn't have to be
anti-Palestinian. In my experience,
there are folks in both this camp as well as in
this camp who care deeply about both Jews and
Arabs and simply want a solution that can be
good for everyone. Even though we tend to see
things in terms of this entire side against this
entire side, I think there’s an argument to be
made that the two positions in the middle actually
have more in common with each other than they do
with the extreme versions of themselves (in that
they both want safety and freedom for everyone).
The main disagreement is just over whether a
two-state solution would be better or whether
a one-state solution would be better. Some
people think a one-state solution would never
work and is incredibly naive. Well, there are
others who think a two-state solution would
never work and is incredibly naive. Which is
why there are also a lot of people who don’t
even argue for one or the other—they just
want peace and are willing to consider both.
The other mistake I made in my first video
was that I said Zionists were a subset of
Jews. What I was trying to convey was that,
when Zionism first arose in the late 1800s,
not all Jews supported it. In fact, up until the
end of World War II, most Jews did not support
it. But here’s the thing. If we fast forward
to today, the vast majority of Zionists are
not even Jews at all. They are Christians, mostly
American Christians. And this is something that
Anti-Zionists point out as being problematic. You
see, according to a certain brand of evangelical
Christianity, the Bible is interpreted as saying
that the Jewish People must be returned to their
homeland—and until this fully happens, Jesus
will not return. So that’s less about supporting
Jewish interests than it is about supporting
their own. And I won't even go into all the
money that US weapons manufacturers make off
of supporting Zionism. Cogito did a really
good video about that—which I'll link to in the
description—if you want to learn more about it.
Instead I want to end by pointing out
that it's not just Anti-Zionism that can
be antisemitic. Zionism can be too. For
example, in the early days of Zionism,
a lot of Europeans supported it because they
didn’t want Jews in their own countries. And
unfortunately this line of thinking still exists
to this day. There are also many Zionists who
look negatively upon the long history of Jews
in the diaspora and are embarrassed by it,
which is a form of internalized antisemitism. In
contrast, many Jewish Anti-Zionists argue that
Jews have a rich history in the diaspora—one
that should be celebrated—and that it’s better
to fight antisemitism wherever its found rather
than try to avoid it by having a Jewish state.
So that was a better look at the terms Zionism
and Anti-Zionism. If you found this series of
videos at all helpful and would like to do
something to support those suffering in Gaza,
I encourage you to donate to an
organization called Connecting Gaza,
a small grassroots organization run by a friend
of mine which is helping people on the ground in
Gaza through personal connections. You can find
the link in the description and pinned comment.
Thanks for watching.